When we think about facilitating a meeting, or indeed facilitating a conversation,
one helpful framework to use is open, narrow, close. So what is that?
These are the three main phases you will have in an interaction.
Opening is exactly what it sounds like.
It’s opening up the issues or the ideas; it’s starting the meeting, kicking it off,
and broadening the perspective of what you’re talking about. Narrowing
is, once you’ve opened everything up, you need to focus,
maybe prioritise, work out really what you want to solve for in that meeting.
And finally, closing — it’s not rocket science — is bringing it all to a successful conclusion:
thinking about next steps, commitments,
making sure everybody agrees what they’ve agreed, making sure you get takeaways, gather takeaways,
so that people move on from the meeting in the most effective way possible.
Open, narrow and close. How do you decide when to move from open to narrowing and then closing?
That depends on several things. It depends on whether this is the last meeting you’ll ever have on the subject, or an initial meeting.
It also depends on how good the ideas need to be. So when you’re planning your workshop, you’ll need to decide how much time
to give to each stage of open, narrow and close.
This takes some experience to get right, but there are some general guidelines.
The opening section, in terms of introduction and sharing the agenda, you want to move through fairly quickly.
People can get frustrated if they don’t get onto the real content quite quickly.
Once you go onto the second part of opening, which is really about opening up the ideas,
you might want to give that more time. At the same time, it’s really about creativity and dynamism.
So you don’t want a twenty-minute brainstorm.
You’ll actually get much better results if you say, “Okay, we’re going to get as many ideas on the table as we can in three minutes. Let’s start the stop clock now.”
People’s energy will be much higher and they will fire those ideas out.
So open, I think, you want to move through; you want to create energy and momentum.
For the narrow phase, that often takes more time and actually more facilitative skill, because really what you’re doing is making hard decisions.
Let’s say you’ve got thirty initiatives on the table and everyone around the room has their own favourites, so there’s much more jeopardy,
and people’s egos are on the line when they’ve offered ideas already.
Do allow good time for that narrowing phase. People need to be on board,
and they need to believe in the fairness of the process that got to the conclusions you get. With closing,
I think you want to again go into momentum mode, because you’re looking for commitments.
So you don’t want to get too stuck down.
Hopefully you’ve actually had some conclusions through the meeting, so it might be partly about restating what has been agreed explicitly at the end, so that everyone is on board.
So I would allow maybe twenty minutes to half an hour for that,
even in a day-long meeting. So those are some of the general guidelines about open, narrow, close and how to portion time throughout the meeting.
Of course, it still depends on context, and understanding what is most important for you to achieve during that interaction.